A Guide to the Photographs of Historic Sites in Charlottesville, Va. 1935-1998
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Photographs of Historic Sites in Charlottesville, Va. 1935-1998
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11405
150 photos: b&w.
The collection contains photographs of churches and a synagogue; commerical buildings; historic buildings; private residences; and railroad bridges and stations. A few structures in Albemarle County are also included.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: Frank Hartman, Charlottesville, Va., 1998 May 15
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains photographs of churches and a synagogue; commerical buildings; historic buildings; private residences; and railroad bridges and stations. A few structures in Albemarle County are also included.
Of interest are photographs of Vinegar Hill taken before its demolition in 1963; a few photographs of area African-Americans including Jack Brown, John Henry and Clarence "Tippy" Rhodes; a 1937 football game of the "Ridge Street Gang" at Gleason's Field, Ridge Street; and photographs of the construction of the foundation for the Nuclear Research Lab at the University of Virginia.
Several of the buildings photographed have since been demolished.
Contents List
- 1952, 1980, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Cocke's Mill, State Route 712 1995
  - "Monticello" 1952
  - Schoolhouse, Crozet 1980
- Churches and Places of Worship 1952-1961, 1989-1998 (Box 1)
  - Beth Israel Temple 1995, 1997
  - Christ Episcopal Church 1996
  - Ebenezer Baptist Church 1998
  - Edge Hill Seminary Chapel 1952
  - First Baptist Church 1998
  - First Christian Church 1998
  - First Presbyterian Church 1953, 1989
  - Holy Comforter Catholic Church 1998
  - Presbyterian Church demolition 1960/61
  - Zion Union Baptist Church n.d.
- Downtown 1977-1997 (Box 1)
  - Former Albemarle County Historical Society Museum, 220 Court Square and 6th Street, N.E. 1996
  - Albemarle County Jail, 409 East High Street 1997
  - Elk's Lodge Home, 411-217 East High Street 1997
  - Magruder Sanitarium, 100 North Jefferson Street 1997
  - Neve Apartments, 313 East Market Street 1997
  - "Social Hall," 107 East Jefferson Street 1977
  - The Wheeler Building, 901 East High Street 1997
  - view looking West on East End of Water Street 1981
- Downtown Mall/East Main Street 1957-1998 (Box 1)
  - "Downtown Newstand" 1995
  - Keller & George 1995
  - M.C. Thomas and A & N Stores fire damage, 420-422 East Main Street 1968
  - National Bank 1998
  - Paramount Theatre, 300 block East Main Street 1958
  - Timberlake Drug Store, 322 East Main Street 1997
  - Virginia National Bank (now NationsBanc), 300 East Main Street 1996
  - The Young Men's Shop 1997
  - Lower East Main Street 1957
  - Construction on Downtown Mall, East Main Street 1975
- East Charlottesville: Belmont/Pantops Mountain/Woolen Mills 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - McIntire Road, steps to nowhere 1995
  - Pantops, looking west on Route 250 to Rivanna River Bridge 1991
  - Rivanna River Dam, Woolen Mills 1995
  - Spudnut Coffee Shop 1992
  - The Young Building, 1102 Carlton Avenue 1996
- Football, Ridge Street Gang, Gleason's Field, Ridge Street 1937 (Box 1)
- Grady Avenue/Preston Avenue 1961, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Carver Inn, Preston Avenue 1961
  - Lucky Food Store, 1207 Grady Avenue 1997
- Historic District 1939-1992
  - Levy Opera House, 350 Park Street 1965
  - Margarita's Headquarters 1939
  - Redland Club, 300 Park Street 1986
  - Tarleton's Oak, corner 9th Street and East High Street n.d.
- Local Residents 1934-1937, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Jack Brown, 86, with Frank C. Hartman 1954
  - John Henry with horse and buggy 1934/1935
  - Clarence "Tippy" Rhodes n.d.
  - unidentified African-American woman, Ridge Street 1937
- Michie Publishing Company Buildings 1992, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Construction of building on CSX Railroad property 1992
  - 609 East Market Street 1995
- Nuclear Research Lab, McCormick Mountain, University of Virginia 1959 (Box 1)
  - Construction 1959
- Railroad Bridges and Stations 1961-1996 (Box 1)
  - Crozet Railroad Station 1996
  - C & O Railroad Station/CSX Railroad Station, East Market Street 1981
  - C & O Railroad Station/CSX Railroad Station, East Water Street 1981
  - C & O Railroad Station/CSX Railroad Station, East Water Street 1992
  - Southern Railroad Bridge over Preston Avenue 1961
  - Southern Railroad Bridge, 700 block West Main Street 1992
  - Southern Railroad Station/Amtrak Station, 810 West Main Street 1992
- Residences 1955-1997 (Box 1)
  - Dabney House, 301 East Market Street 1997
  - Everett House, 213 7th Street 1995
  - Livers House/1817 Bed and Breakfast, 1211 West Main Street 1996
  - Massie-Smith House, 211 4th Street, N.E. 1996
  - Massie-Smith House/Massie-Wills House, 211 4th Street/215 4th Street 1996
  - Massie Wills House, 215 4th Street 1996
  - Pace-Wranek House, 2nd Street, S.W. 1996
  - Turner House, 400 Altamont Circle 1997
  - Wertenbaker House, Wertland Street 1980, 1990
  - Woolen Mills Manager residence 1997
  - 127 10th Street, N.W. 1965
  - 1111-1113 West Main Street, built by John Knowles 1989
  - Northside of state Route 676 prior to entering State Route 743 (imprisoned Yankee prisoners during Civil War?) 1955
- Residences--High Street 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Dinwiddie House, 109 East High Street 1997
  - Minor-Nelson House ("Nelson Sanitorium"), 201 East High Street 1996
  - Nelson House, 205 East High Street 1997
  - Sterling-Lewis House, 101 East High Street 1997
  - M.C. Thomas House, 111 West High Street 1997
  - Trice-Towe House, 211 East High Street 1997
- Residences--Jefferson Street 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Butler-Norris House, 410 East Jefferson Street 1997
  - Butler-Norris House/Norris-McCue Building, 410-412 East Jefferson Street 1997
  - Farish House, 500 East Jefferson Street 1996
  - Johnson-Mundy House, 400 East Jefferson Street 1997
  - Kelly-Bragg Store House, 418 East Jefferson 1996
- Vinegar Hill 1963 Dec (Box 1)
  - 20 photographs taken just prior to destruction, 1963 1963
    includes shots of Homestead Grill, Leach's Cafe, Kane Furniture, Coney Island Lunch, M.C. Thomas, S & P Retail Store, and City Taxi
- West Main Street 1952-1998 (Box 1)
  - Albemarle Hotel 1980
  - Holsinger Studio/Back Alley Disc 1995
  - Monticello Antique Shop, 1000 West Main Street 1960, 1965
  - Paxton Place, 503 West Main Street 1998
  - Pitts-Inge Grocery Store (now Awful Arthur's Seafood), 331-333 West Main Street 1952
  - Queen Charlotte Hotel 1955
  - Recreation Hall (now Southern Culture) and 600-700 block 1980
  - Starr Hill, Cotton Exchange, and 700 block 1992
  - University Theatre, between 13th and 14th Street 1990
  - West Main Street looking east from Southern Railroad Bridge 1996